Finding Aid for the George Antheil Papers PASC-M.0043
UCLA Library Special Collections
George Antheil papers
1935-1957
UCLA Library Special Collections
Antheil, George
PASC-M.0043
20 Linear Feet (2 document boxes, 35 flat boxes, and 5 oversize flat boxes)
This collection consists primarily of scores for music composed by George Antheil for film and television.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Peter Antheil, 1980, 1992, 2006. Two items in Series 3 (The Wish, Toccata No. 2) gift of Irwin Parnes, 1978.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9942303243606533
Biographical Note
Composer George Antheil was born June 8, 1900 in Trenton, New Jersey. He studied piano and composition from an early age and moved to Europe in 1922, finally landing in Paris after a year in Berlin. While in Paris, Antheil befriended a number of avant-garde artists and writers, and composed several works that called for unorthodox instrumentation. His best-known work Ballet Mécanique (1924), originally intended to accompany a Fernand Léger film, included sirens, bells, and airplane propellers. Following its unfavorable premier in New York in 1927, Antheil continued to compose concert works, ballets, and operas, while dividing his time between Europe and the U.S. In 1936, he settled in Los Angeles, where he composed music for numerous films and also continued to write classical works during the 1940s and 1950s. In addition to music, Antheil had several other pursuits including writing, endocrinology, and technological invention. George Antheil died in New York on February 12, 1959.
For a catalog of Antheil's music see Linda Whitesitt's The Life and Music of George Antheil 1900-1959, 1983. Also see Antheil's autobiography, Bad Boy of Music.
Scope and Content
This collection consists primarily of music composed by George Antheil for film and television. Manuscript and reproduction scores are present for numerous films including Ben Hecht's Once in a Blue Moon (1935), John Parker's Dementia (1955), and Stanley Kramer's Not as a Stranger (1955) and The Pride and the Passion (1957). Also present are scores for episodes of the CBS television documentary series The Twentieth Century.
The collection also includes a small number of songs and other musical compositions, including his opera The Wish, as well as writings by Antheil about World War II, mostly written for Los Angeles radio programs.
Organization and Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series 1. Film projects
Series 2. Television projects
Series 3. Other musical compositions
Series 4. World War II writings
Series 5. Correspondence
Series 6. Sound recordings
Related Material
George Antheil Papers available at the Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Columbia University
George Antheil Papers available at the Performing Arts Library, New York Public Library
George and Böske Antheil Papers available at the Music Division, Library of Congress.
Composers -- Archives.; Television music -- Scores and parts.; Motion picture music -- Scores and parts.; American composers.
- Series 1. Film projects
  Scope and Content
  Antheil composed music for films by directors Cecil B. DeMille, John Huston, Nicholas Ray, Ben Hecht and Stanley Kramer, among others. Series includes manuscript and reproduction scores and parts, including a holograph score for the surrealist noir film Dementia (1955). Material is generally undated; dates following titles are those of the film's release. Some oversized scores are housed separately.
  The films Harlem Sketches and Orchids to Charlie were shorts.
  - Angels over Broadway (1940) (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
  - The Buccaneer (1938) (Box 1, Folder 4-6)
  - Dementia (1955), 1953 (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
  - The Fighting Kentuckian (1949) (Box 2, Folder 4, Box 3, Folder 1-2)
  - Harlem Sketches [Harlem Picture] (1935) (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - House By the River [Floodtide] (1950) (Box 3, Folder 4-5, Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Hunters of the Deep (1955) (Box 4, Folder 2-5, Box 6, Folder 1-3, Box 5, Box 37, Folder 2-7)
  - In a Lonely Place (1950) (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - The Juggler (1953) (Box 6, Folder 5, Box 7, Folder 1-2)
  - Knock On Any Door (1949) (Box 7, Folder 3-4)
  - Not As a Stranger (1955) (Box 7, Folder 5-6, Box 36, Box 12, Folder 1-2, Box 8, Box 9, Box 10, Box 11)
  - Once in a Blue Moon (1935) (Box 13, Box 12, Folder 3-5)
  - Orchids to Charlie [Orchids for Charlie] (1941) (Box 14, Box 39, Folder 3-6, Box 15, Folder 1-2)
  - The Plainsman (1936) (Box 15, Folder 3, Box 16, Folder 1)
  - The Plainsman and the Lady (1946) (Box 16, Folder 2-3)
  - The Pride and the Passion (1957): Full score manuscripts (Box 39, Folder 1-2, Box 38)
  - The Pride and the Passion (1957): Parts (Box 16, Folder 4, Box 17, Box 18, Box 19, Box 20, Box 21, Box 22, Box 23, Box 24, Box 25)
  - The Pride and the Passion (1957): Sketches and conductors scores (Box 27, Folder 2, Box 26)
  - The Pride and the Passion (1957): Clippings and ephemera (Box 27, Folder 1)
  - The Pride and the Passion (1957): Songs (Box 27, Folder 3)
    Also includes some material from The Young Don't Cry (1957).
  - The Pride and the Passion (1957): Photostat scores (Box 27, Folder 4-5)
  - Repeat Performance (1947) (Box 28, Folder 1-2)
  - Sirocco (1951) (Box 28, Folder 3-5)
  - The Sniper (1952) (Box 1, Folder 7-9)
    Scope and Contents
    Box 8 also includes score "Death Ride" from Death of a Salesman (Columbia, 1951) by Alex North.
  - Specter of the Rose (1946) (Box 29, Box 37, Folder 1, Box 30, Folder 1-3)
  - That Brennan Girl (1946) (Box 30, Folder 4-5)
  - Tokyo Joe (1949) (Box 31, Folder 1)
  - We Were Strangers [Rough Sketch] (1949) (Box 31, Folder 2)
- Series 2. Television projects
  Primarily contains scores of music written for the CBS documentary series The Twentieth Century, which aired from 1957 to 1968.
  - The Twentieth Century: Churchill, Man of the Century [A Little Mouse of Thought] (Box 32, Folder 1)
  - The Twentieth Century: D-Day Attack (Box 32, Folder 2)
  - The Twentieth Century: Gandhi (Box 32, Folder 3)
  - The Twentieth Century: Guided Missile (Box 32, Folder 4)
  - The Twentieth Century: Liberation of Paris (Box 32, Folder 5-6)
  - The Twentieth Century: Mission Outer Space (Box 33, Folder 1-2)
  - The Twentieth Century: Remagen Bridge (Box 33, Folder 3)
  - The Twentieth Century: War in China (Box 33, Folder 4)
  - The Twentieth Century: War in Spain (Box 33, Folder 5)
  - The Twentieth Century: The Windsors (Box 33, Folder 6)
  - Woman Without Shadow (Box 35, Folder 2)
  - Television cues: The Twentieth Century (Box 34, Folder 1)
  - Television cues (Box 34, Folder 2-4)
    Cues for television programs of various genres; specific productions unknown.
- Series 3. Other musical compositions
  - Songs (Box 35, Folder 3-5)
  - Requiem (Box 35, Folder 6)
    Possibly Requiem for the Soldiers of the Last War, 1927.
  - Toccata No. 2, [1948] (Box 35, Folder 7)
    Piano solo, reproduction.
  - The Wish, [1954] (Box 35, Folder 8-9)
    Orchestral score for the opera, reproduction.
  - Unidentified scores (Box 40, Box 42, Folder 5)
    Includes music written for unidentified film or television projects.
  - Instructions for system of orchestral indication, 1957 (Box 35, Folder 1)
  - Chansons de France by Marcel Vigneras (publication), 1941 (Box 42, Folder 6)
- Series 4. World War II writings
  Antheil's book The Shape of the War to Come (published anonymously in 1940), along with magazine articles written about World War II, led him to be hired by Los Angeles publisher Manchester Boddy to analyze the war for his radio program. In 1943, Antheil left Boddy's program for John Nesbitt's The Passing Parade (CBS), where he continued as a war analyst.
  This series contains scripts, essays and drafts for both radio programs. Also present are drafts and parts of drafts of other World War II writings that may have been for either radio program, or for publication elsewhere; a clipping of Antheil's Esquire article "So Smells Defeat" (Nov 1936); and articles on strategic geography, author unknown.
  - Manchester Boddy program, 1942-1943 (Box 41, Folder 1)
  - John Nesbitt's The Passing Parade, 1943-1944 (Box 42, Folder 1-2, Box 41, Folder 2-9)
  - Other World War II writings, [1936], undated (Box 42, Folder 3-4)
- Series 5. Correspondence, 1955 (Box 42, Folder 7)
- Series 6. Sound recordings (Box 27)
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  RESTRICTED ACCESS: Use of audio material requires production of listening copies.
  Five 78 rpm discs with songs most likely from the films The Pride and the Passion and The Young Don't Cry, as well as other songs with music written by Antheil.